<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter xml:id="chapter-JCR">
  <title>Introduction to JCR</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>
      Java Content Repository API as well as other Java language related standards is created within the Java Community Process (http://jcp.org/) as a result of collaboration of an expert group and the Java community. It is known as <ulink url="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=170">JSR-170</ulink> (Java Specification Request).
	  This chapter is for people new to eXo JCR that walks you through an overview of outstanding advantages of JCR. Especially, you will also learn about the following core topics:
    </para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="JCRref.Introduction.JCRArchitecture">JCR architecture</link></emphasis></para>
			<para>Introduction to 2 core factors of the JCR architecture: eXo Repository Service and Workspace Data Model.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="JCR.CompatibilityLevels">Compatibility levels</link></emphasis></para>
			<para>Details of 2 compliance levels and a set of optional features.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </abstract>
    <!-- Why use JCR & What does eXo do -->    
<para xml:id="JCRref.Introduction.WhyuseJCR">
  <citetitle>
    <emphasis role="bold">Why Use JCR?</emphasis>
  </citetitle>
</para>
    
    <para>Do you know how your website data are stored? Images can be 
    stored in a file system, and metadata are in some dedicated files, for example, in <filename>.xml</filename> files, and 
	text documents and PDFs are stored in different folders
    with metadata in another repositories and in a proprietary
    structure. How do you manage updating these data and access rights? 
	Where and how do u start if your leader asks you to manage different versions of
    each document? The larger your website is, the more you need a
    <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_management_system">Content
    Management Systems</ulink> (CMS) which tackles all these issues.</para> 

    <para>These CMS solutions are provided by different vendors and each vendor
    provides its own API for interfacing the proprietary content repository.
    The developers MUST deal with this and need to learn about the
    vendor-specific API. If you intend to switch to a different
    vendor in future, everything will be different, for example, you need a new
    implementation or a new interface.</para>

    <para>JCR provides a unique Java interface that allows you to interact with both text
    and binary data, and to deal with any kind and amount of metadata of your
    documents. JCR supplies methods for storing, updating, deleting
    and retrieving your data without being dependent on the fact that the data is stored
    in a RDBMS, in a file system or as an XML document. The JCR interface is also defined as classes and methods
    for searching, versioning, access control, locking and observation.</para>

    <para>Furthermore, the export and import functionality is specified so that a switch to a different vendor is always possible.</para>  

<para xml:id="JCRref.Introduction.WhateXodo">
  <citetitle>
      <emphasis role="bold">What does eXo do?</emphasis>
  </citetitle> 
</para>

    <para>eXo fully complies with <ulink url="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=170">JSR 170</ulink>; therefore with
    eXo JCR you can use a vendor-independent API. It means that you could switch to a different vendor whenever. By using the standard, you can reduce your 
    lifecycle cost and long-term risk.</para>

    <note>
		<para>eXo offers not only JCR, but also the complete solution for ECM (Enterprise Content Management) and for WCM (Web Content Management).</para>
	</note>
	
	<!--1.1. JCR architecture -->
    <xi:include href="Introduction/jcr-architecture.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
	<!--1.2. Compatibility levels -->
	<xi:include href="Introduction/jcr-compatibility-levels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</chapter>