<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="chapter-Administration-PerformanceTuning">
  <title>Performance tuning</title>

    <para>This section will show you possible ways of improving JCR.</para>

    <para>It is intended for eXo Platform administrators and those who want to use JCR features.</para>

	<citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.JBossASTuning"><emphasis role="bold">JBoss AS Tuning</emphasis></para>
	</citetitle>

      <para>You can use <parameter>maxThreads</parameter> parameter to
      increase maximum amount of threads that can be launched in AS instance.
      This can improve performance if you need a high level of concurrency.
      Also, you can use the <code>-XX:+UseParallelGC</code> java directory to use
      parallel garbage collector.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>Beware of setting <parameter>maxThreads</parameter> too big,
        this can cause <exceptionname>OutOfMemoryError</exceptionname>. There is <code>maxThreads=1250</code> on the machine:
        <itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>7.5 GB memory</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>4 EC2 Compute Units (2 virtual cores with 2 EC2 Compute Units each)</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>850 GB instance storage (2×420 GB plus 10 GB root partition)</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>64-bit platform</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>I/O Performance: High</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>API name: m1.large</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>java -Xmx 4g</para>
		  </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
	   </para>
      </tip>

    <citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.JCRCacheTuning"><emphasis role="bold">JCR Cache Tuning</emphasis></para>
	</citetitle>
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Cache size</emphasis>: The JCR-cluster implementation is built using JBoss Cache as
        distributed, replicated cache. But there is one particularity related to
        remove action in it. Speed of this operation depends on the actual size
        of cache. Because there are currently many nodes in cache, it will take you much time to remove any specific
        node (subtree) from the cache.
      </para>
    </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Eviction</emphasis>: Manipulations with eviction <parameter>wakeUpInterval</parameter>
		value does not affect performance. Performance results with values
		from 500 up to 3000 are approximately equal.</para>
      </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Transaction Timeout</emphasis>: Using short timeout for long transactions, such as Export/Import,
		removing huge subtree defined timeout, may cause <exceptionname>TransactionTimeoutException</exceptionname>.</para>
      </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  <citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.Clustering"><emphasis role="bold">Clustering</emphasis></para>
  </citetitle>
	
      <para>For performance, it is better to have <parameter>loadbalancer</parameter>, the database server, and
      shared NFS on different computers. If one node gets more load than others, you can decrease this load by using the load
      value in the load balancer.</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">JGroups configuration</emphasis>: It is recommended that you use the "multiplexer
        stack" feature available in JGroups.
        This feature is set by default in eXo JCR that offers higher performance in cluster and
        reduces the network connections. If there are two or
        more clusters in your network, check that they use different
        ports and different cluster names.
      </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Write performance in cluster</emphasis>: The eXo JCR implementation uses Lucene
        indexing engine to provide
        search capabilities. However, Lucene causes some limitations for write opertation, for example, it can perform
        indexing only in one thread. That is why the write performance in cluster is not
        higher than that in a singleton environment.
        Data is indexed on coordinator node, so increasing write-load on cluster may
        lead to ReplicationTimeout exception. It occurs because writing threads
        queue in the indexer and under high load timeout for replication to
        coordinator will be exceeded.
      </para>
      <note>
      <para>It is recommended to exceed the
        <parameter>replTimeout</parameter>
        value in cache configurations in case
        of high write-load.
      </para>
      </note>
      </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Replication timeout</emphasis>: Some operations may take too much time. So if you get
		<exceptionname>ReplicationTimeoutException</exceptionname>, try
		increasing the replication timeout:</para>
      
      <programlisting language="xml">   &lt;clustering mode="replication" clusterName="${jbosscache-cluster-name}"&gt;
      ...
      &lt;sync replTimeout="60000" /&gt;
   &lt;/clustering&gt;
   </programlisting>
		<para>The value is set in miliseconds.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 <citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.JVMParameters"><emphasis role="bold">JVM parameters</emphasis></para>
 </citetitle>
   <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">PermGen space size</emphasis>: If you intend to use Infinispan, you will have to
        increase the
        PermGen size to at least 256 Mo due to the latest versions of JGroups
        that are needed by Infinispan (please note that Infinspan is only
        dedicated to the community for now, no support will be provided). In case you intend to use JBoss Cache, you can
        keep using JGroups 2.6.13.GA which means that you do not need to increase the PermGen size.
      </para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  <citetitle>
    <para xml:id="JCR.JDBCDataContainerConfig.ForseQueryHints"><emphasis role="bold">Forse Query Hints</emphasis></para>
  </citetitle>

    <para>Some databases support hints to increase query performance (like
    Oracle, MySQL, and more). eXo JCR have separate Complex Query implementation
    for Orcale dialect, that uses query hints to increase performance for few
    important queries.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>To enable this option, put next configuration property:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;workspace name="ws" auto-init-root-nodetype="nt:unstructured"&gt;
  &lt;container class="org.exoplatform.services.jcr.impl.storage.jdbc.JDBCWorkspaceDataContainer"&gt;
    &lt;properties&gt;
      &lt;property name="dialect" value="oracle"/&gt;
      &lt;property name="force.query.hints" value="true" /&gt;
      ......</programlisting>
	    </listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>The Query hints are enabled by default.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>eXo JCR uses query hints only for Complex Query Oracle dialect. For all other dialects, this parameter is ignored.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</section>
