<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="chapter-Administration-PerformanceTuning">
  <title>Performance tuning</title>

    <para>This section will show you possible ways of improving JCR.</para>

    <para>It is intended to GateIn Administrators and those who wants to use
    JCR features.</para>

	<citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.JBossASTuning"><emphasis role="bold">JBoss AS Tuning</emphasis></para>
	</citetitle>

      <para>You can use <parameter>maxThreads</parameter> parameter to
      increase maximum amount of threads that can be launched in AS instance.
      This can improve performance if you need a high level of concurrency.
      also you can use <code>-XX:+UseParallelGC</code> java directory to use
      paralel garbage collector.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>Beware of setting <parameter>maxThreads</parameter> too big,
        this can cause <exceptionname>OutOfMemoryError</exceptionname>. We've
        got it with <code>maxThreads=1250</code> on such machine:
        <itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>7.5 GB memory</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>4 EC2 Compute Units (2 virtual cores with 2 EC2 Compute Units each)</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>850 GB instance storage (2×420 GB plus 10 GB root partition)</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>64-bit platform</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>I/O Performance: High</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>API name: m1.large</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			<para>java -Xmx 4g</para>
		  </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
	   </para>
      </tip>

    <citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.JCRCacheTuning"><emphasis role="bold">JCR Cache Tuning</emphasis></para>
	</citetitle>
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Cache size</emphasis>: The JCR-cluster implementation is built using JBoss Cache as
      distributed, replicated cache. But there is one particularity related to
      remove action in it. Speed of this operation depends on the actual size
      of cache. As many nodes are currently in cache as much time is needed to
      remove one particular node (subtree) from it.</para>
      </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Eviction</emphasis>: Manipulations with eviction <parameter>wakeUpInterval</parameter>
		value doestn't affect on performance. Performance results with values
		from 500 up to 3000 are approximately equal.</para>
      </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Transaction Timeout</emphasis>: Using short timeout for long transactions such as Export/Import,
		removing huge subtree defined timeout may cause <exceptionname>TransactionTimeoutException</exceptionname>. [TODO] put
		recomended timeout value.</para>
      </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  <citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.Clustering"><emphasis role="bold">Clustering</emphasis></para>
  </citetitle>
	
      <para>For performance, it is better to have loadbalacer, DB server and
      shared NFS on different computers. If in some reasons you see that one
      node gets more load than others you can decrease this load using load
      value in load balancer.</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">JGroups configuration</emphasis>: It is recommended to use "multiplexer stack" feature present in
		JGroups. It is set by default in eXo JCR and offers higher performance
		in cluster, using less network connections also. If there are two or
		more clusters in your network, please check that they use different
		ports and different cluster names.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Write performance in cluster</emphasis>: The eXo JCR implementation uses Lucene indexing engine to provide
		search capabilities. But Lucene brings some limitations for write
		operations: it can perform indexing only in one thread. Thats why write
		performance in cluster is not higher than in singleton environment. Data
		is indexed on coordinator node, so increasing write-load on cluster may
		lead to ReplicationTimeout exception. It occurs because writing threads
		queue in the indexer and under high load timeout for replication to
		coordinator will be exceeded.</para>
		<para>Taking in consideration this fact, it is recommended to exceed
		<parameter>replTimeout</parameter> value in cache configurations in case
		of high write-load.</para>
      </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Replication timeout</emphasis>: Some operations may take too much time. So if you get
		<exceptionname>ReplicationTimeoutException</exceptionname> try
		increasing replication timeout:</para>
      
      <programlisting language="xml">   &lt;clustering mode="replication" clusterName="${jbosscache-cluster-name}"&gt;
      ...
      &lt;sync replTimeout="60000" /&gt;
   &lt;/clustering&gt;
   </programlisting>
		<para>The value is set in miliseconds.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 <citetitle>
      <para xml:id="JCR.PerformanceTuningGuide.PerformanceTuningGuide.JVMParameters"><emphasis role="bold">JVM parameters</emphasis></para>
 </citetitle>
   <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">PermGen space size</emphasis>: If you intend to use Infinispan, you will have to increase the
			PermGen size to at least 256 Mo due to the latest versions of JGroups
			that are needed by Infinispan (please note that Infinspan is only
			dedicated to the community for now, no support will be provided). In
			case, you intend to use JBoss Cache, you can keep on using JGroups
			2.6.13.GA which means that you don't need to increase the PermGen
			size.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  <citetitle>
    <para xml:id="JCR.JDBCDataContainerConfig.ForseQueryHints"><emphasis role="bold">Forse Query Hints</emphasis></para>
  </citetitle>

    <para>Some databases supports hints to increase query performance (like
    Oracle, MySQL, etc). eXo JCR have separate Complex Query implementation
    for Orcale dialect, that uses query hints to increase performance for few
    important queries.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>To enable this option put next configuration property:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;workspace name="ws" auto-init-root-nodetype="nt:unstructured"&gt;
  &lt;container class="org.exoplatform.services.jcr.impl.storage.jdbc.JDBCWorkspaceDataContainer"&gt;
    &lt;properties&gt;
      &lt;property name="dialect" value="oracle"/&gt;
      &lt;property name="force.query.hints" value="true" /&gt;
      ......</programlisting>
	    </listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>The Query hints are enabled by default.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>eXo JCR uses query hints only for Complex Query Oracle dialect. For all other dialects this parameter is ignored.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</section>
